<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of the Longobards (English)</title>
<author>Paul, the Deacon</author>
        <authorURN>urn:cts:latinLit:stoa0224</authorURN>

        <language ident="lat">English</language>
    <urlParsed>https://elfinspell.com/MedievalMatter/PaultheDeacon-PaulusDiaconus/HistoryOfTheLangobards/PaulTheDeacon-Appendix2.html</urlParsed>
    <dateParsed>Wed Feb 08 2023 18:20:27 GMT-0600 (Central Standard Time)</dateParsed>
    <Translator>William Dudley Foulke</Translator>
    <Publisher>Lacus Curtius</Publisher>
    <Authority>Bill Thayer</Authority>
    <Source_Publisher>Longman, Green &amp; Co.</Source_Publisher>
    <Source_Pub_Place>New York</Source_Pub_Place>
    <Source_Pub_Date>1906</Source_Pub_Date>
  </titleStmt>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>

      <div type="chapter" n="frontmatter"> 
         <p>Paul twice refers to a prologue to the Edict of Rothari as one of the sources of his history (Jacobi, 4). In book I, chap. 21 he says: “At the same time Waccho fell upon the Suavi and subjected them to his authority. If any one may think that this is a lie and not the truth of the matter, let him read over the prologue of the edict which king Rothari composed (<I>relegat prologum edicti quem rex Rothari  *  *  * composuit</I><ref type="note" target="6" />) of the laws of the Langobards and he will find this written in almost all the manuscripts as we have inserted it in this little history.” Also in book IV, chapter 42 he says “it was now indeed the seventy-seventh year from the time when the Langobards had come into Italy as that king (Rothari) bore witness in a prologue to his Edict.”
             </p>
         <p>The last passage apparently refers to a short preface in Rothari’s laws (Edicti Codices, M. G. LL., IV, p. 1), although the 76th year and not the 77th is there mentioned. But this preface contains no account of the overthrow of the Suavi by Waccho, Bethmann (p. 351 <I>et seq</I>.), Baude di Vesme (Edicta Regum Langobardorum, Aug. Taur., 1855, p. LXXI; see Jacobi, 4, 5) and others therefore believe that Paul’s reference must be attributed to a short history of the Origin of the Nation of the Langobards contained in three manuscripts (of Modena, Madrid and La Cava<ref type="note" target="7" />) and in a fourth form greatly interpolated in the so-called Chronicon Gothanum (Jacobi, 4). A translation of the Origo as contained in these three MSS. is here given:<ref type="note" target="8" />
             </p>
    </div>
  <body>  
  <div type="chapter" n="1">  
    <head>The Origin of the Nation of Langobards</head>

         <p>There is an island<ref type="note" target="9" /> that is called Scadanan,<ref type="note" target="10" /> which is interpreted “destruction,”<ref type="note" target="11" /> in the regions of the north, where many people dwell. Among these there was a small people that was called the Winniles. And with them was a woman, Gambara by name, and she had two sons. Ybor was the name of one and Agio the name of the other. They, with their mother, Gambara by name, held the sovereignty over the Winniles. Then the leaders of the Wandals, that is, Ambri and Assi, moved with their army, and said to the Winniles: “Either pay us tributes or prepare yourselves for battle and fight with us.” Then answered Ybor and Agio, with their mother Gambara: “It is better for us to make ready the battle than to pay tribute to the Wandals.” Then Ambri and Assi, that is, the leaders of the Wandals, asked Godan that he should give them the victory over the Winniles. Godan answered, saying: “Whom I shall first see when at sunrise, to them will I give the victory.” At that time Gambara with her two sons, that is, Ybor and Agio, who were chiefs over the Winniles, besought Frea, the wife of Godan, to be propitious to the Winnilis. Then Frea gave counsel that at sunrise the Winniles should come, and that their women, with their hair let down around the face in the likeness of a beard, should also come with their husbands. Then when it became bright, while the sun was rising, Frea, the wife of Godan, turned around the bed where her husband was lying and put his face toward the east and awakened him. And he, looking at them, saw the Winniles and their women having their hair let down around the face. And he says, “Who are those Long-beards?” And Frea said to Godan, “As you have given them a name, give them also the victory.” And he gave them the victory, so that they should defend themselves according to his counsel and obtain the victory. From that time the Winniles were called Langobards. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="2">
         <p>And the Langobards moved thence and came to Golaida and afterwards they occupied the aldionates of Anthaib and Bainaib and Burgundaib. And it is said that they made for themselves a king, Agilmund by name, the son of Agio, of the race of Gugingus. And after him reigned Laiamicho of the race of Gugingus.<ref type="note" target="12" /> And after him reigned Lethuc and it is said that he reigned about forty years. And after him reigned Aldihoc the son of Lethuc. And after him reigned Godehoc. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="3">
         <p>At that time king Audoachari went forth from Ravenna with the army of the Alani and came into Rugiland and fought with the Rugians and killed Theuvane king of the Rugians, and led many captives with him into Italy. Then the Langobards departed from their own territories and dwelt some years in Rugiland. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="4">
         <p>Claffo, the son of Godehoc reigned after him. And after him reigned Tato the son of Claffo. The Langobards settled three years in the fields of Feld. Tato fought with Rodolf king of the Heruli and killed him and carried off his banner (<I>vando</I>) and helmet. After him the Heruli had no kingly office. And Wacho the son of Unichis killed king Tato his paternal uncle together with Zuchilo. And Wacho fought, and Ildichis the son of Tato fought, and Ildichis fled to the Gippidi where he died. And to avenge his wrong the Gypidis made war with the Langobards. At this time Wacho bent the Suabians under the dominion of the Langobards. Wacho had three wives: (first) Raicunda, daughter of Fisud king of the Turingi. After her he took as his wife Austrigusa a girl of the Gippidi.<ref type="note" target="13" /> And Wacho had from Austrigusa two daughters; the name of one was Wisigarda whom he gave in marriage to Theudipert king<ref type="note" target="14" /> of the Franks, and the name of the second was Walderada whom Scusuald king of the Franks had as his wife, but having her in hatred he transferred her to Garipald for a wife. He had as his third wife the daughter of the king of the Heruli, Silinga by name. From her he had a son, Waltari by name. Wacho died and his son Waltari reigned seven years without posterity.<ref type="note" target="15" /> These werall Lethinges. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="5">
         <p>And after Waltari, reigned Auduin.<ref type="note" target="16" /> He led the Langobards into Pannonia. And there reigned after him Albuin, his son, whose mother is Rodelenda. At that time Albuin fought with the king of the Gippidi, Cunimund by name, and Cunimund died in that battle and the Gippidi were subjugated. Albuin took as his wife Cunimund’s daughter Rosemund, whom he had captured as booty, since his wife Flutsuinda, who was the daughter of Flothar, king of the Franks, had already died. From her he had a daughter by name Albsuinda. And the Langobards dwelt forty-two years<ref type="note" target="17" /> in Pannonia. This Albuin led into Italy the Langobards who were invited by Narses chief of the secretaries. And Albuin, king of the Langobards, moved out of Pannonia in the month of April after<ref type="note" target="18" /> Easter in the first indiction. In the second indiction, indeed, they began to plunder Italy, but in the third indiction he became master of Italy. Albuin reigned in Italy three years, and was killed in Verona in the palace by Rosemund his wife and Hilmichis upon the advice of Peritheo. Hilmichis wished to be king and could not because the Langobards wanted to slay him. Then Rosemund sent word to the prefect Longinus that he should receive her in Ravenna. When Longinus presently heard this he rejoiced; he sent a ship of the public service and they brought Rosemund and Hilmichis and Albsuinda, king Albuin’s daughter, and conducted all the treasures of the Langobards with them to Ravenna. Then the prefect Longinus began to persuade Rosemund to kill Hilmichis and become the wife of Longinus. Having given ear to his counsel, she mixed poison and, after the bath, gave it to him (Hilmichis) to drink in a goblet.<ref type="note" target="19" /> But when Hilmichis had drunk, he knew that he had drunk something pernicious. He commanded that Rosemund herself should drink, although unwilling, and they both died. Then the prefect Longinus took the treasure of the Langobards and commanded Albsuinda, the daughter of king Albuin, to be put in a ship, and sent her over to Constantinople to the emperor. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="6">
         <p>The rest of the Langobards set over themselves a king named Cleph, of the stock of Beleos, and Cleph reigned two years and died. And the dukes of the Langobards administered justice for twelve years and after these things they set up over themselves a king named Autari, the son of Cleph. And Autari took as his wife Theudelenda, a daughter of Garipald and of Walderada from Bavaria. And with Theudelenda came her brother named Gundoald, and king Autari appointed him duke in the city of Asta. And Autari reigned seven years. And Acquo,<ref type="note" target="20" /> the Thuringian duke,<ref type="note" target="21" /> departed from Turin and united himself with queen Theudelenda and became king of the Langobards. And he killed his rebel dukes Zangrolf of Verona, Mimulf of the island of St. Julian and Gaidulf of Bergamo, and others who were rebels. And Acquo begot of Theudelenda a daughter, Gunperga<ref type="note" target="22" /> by name. And Acquo reigned six years, and after him Aroal reigned twelve years.<ref type="note" target="23" /> And after him reined Rothari, of the race of Arodus and he destroyed the city and fortresses of the Romans which were around the coasts from the neighborhood of Luna<ref type="note" target="24" /> up to the land of the Franks and in the east up to Ubitergium (Oderzo). And he fought near the river Scultenna,<ref type="note" target="25" /> and there fell on the side of the Romans the number of eight thousand. </p>
        </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="7">
         <p>And Rothari reigned seventeen years. And after him reigned Aripert nine years. And after him reigned Grimoald.<ref type="note" target="26" /> At this time the emperor Constantine departed from Constantinople and came into the territories of Campania and turned back to Sicily and was killed by his own people. And Grimoald reigned nine years, and after him Berthari reigned.<ref type="note" target="27" /> </p>
        </div>
        </body>
    <div type="backmatter">
        <p>Bluhme says (Mon. Germ. Hist. Leges, IV, p. 646, note) that several reasons indicate that the text of this Origo was written when Berthari (Perctarit) was king. Baude di Vesme attributes it to Rothari’s time, and believes that the final statements were subsequent additions. Bethmann (p. 414) attributes it to the seventh year of the reign of Grimoald.  (See also Jacobi, 8, 9).</p>
        <p>Of the fourth text, the <I>Chronicon Gothanum</I>, Hodgkin remarks (V, 69), “To one manuscript of the Lombard laws, that is now preserved in the ducal library of Gotha, there is prefixed an introduction on the history of the Lombards which evidently shows a certain affinity to the Origo, but is of later date, and contains some curious additions as to the early migrations of the race. It continues the history down to the time of Charles the Great, and was probably written under his son Pipin, (A. D. 807-810).  (See also Schmidt, 10.) The author is a strongly-pronounced Christian, and loves to support his statements by quotations from Scripture. He is, however, very imperfectly informed as to early Lombard history; he wrote, as will be seen, two hundred and fifty years after the invasion, and it does not seem wise to place much dependence on his statements where they differ from those of the Origo.”</p>
        <p>The question what Paul took from the Origo has been exhaustively discussed, first, in Jacobi’s monograph, “The Sources of Paul the Deacon’s History of the Langobards” (Halle, 1877), and, secondly, in an article by Theodore Mommsen published in the Neues Archiv, Vol. V, 53, <I>et seq.</I> (1879). Let us consider these discussions in their order.</p>
        <p>According to Jacobi (p. 10) Paul took from the Origo, first, the account of the origin of the Langobards in the North. With the aid of Pliny, he identified Scadan or Scadanan (I, 2; Pliny, Nat. Hist., IV, 27 [13]) with Scadinavia. The description he gives of that “island” may be from an oral account. The words of the Origo, “In the regions of the north where many people dwell,” give occasion for Paul’s first chapter, showing the advantage of northern lands for the development of powerful peoples. In this he garnished his account from Isidore, as well hereafter appear.</p>
        <p>Paul then causes the Langobards to come forth from Scadinavia (I, 3) on account of over-population, “although other causes are asserted for their emigration.” The Origo assigns no cause, but the Chronicon Gothanum says in its confused way, “The ancient ancestors of the Langobards assert from their parent Gambara for what purpose was their departure or emigration,” etc. They came first to Scoringa (I, 7), where they remained a long time. Here they were attacked by the Wandals under Ambri and Assi. Now Paul (I, 7 and 8), following the Origo, relates the saga by which the victory was accorded them by Wotan with Frea’s help and they acquired the name of Langobards. Jacobi believes (p. 13) that the name Scoringa was dropped from the text of the Origo as it has come down to us, and that the derivation of the name of the Langobards from their method of wearing their hair is also drawn from some earlier copy of the Origo, although this addition is lacking in the three manuscripts. The Chronicon Gothanum states that they changed their name to Langobards “because their beard was long and never shaved.” These last words come from Isidore (Etymology, IX, 2, 94), but Jacobi (p. 13) considers it probable that they were derived therefrom through the Origo, since there is found elsewhere in the Origo traces of the use of Isidore (Jacobi, 14).</p>
        <p>The Langobards obtain the victory over the Vandals (I, 10) but a famine soon breaks out in Scoringa and they resolve to emigrate (I, 11, 12) to Mauringa. But they must pass through the territory of the Assipitti who refuse them transit. By cunning the Langobards divert a threatened attack, and a duel between a champion of the Assipitti and a Langobard slave opens the way to them. To increase the number of men capable of bearing arms they bestow freedom upon many of their slaves by the ancient symbol of the arrow (See Hammerstein, Bardengau, 65). The Origo contains nothing of all this (Jacobi, 15).</p>
        <p>The Origo knows nothing of the famine which compelled the people to emigrate from Scoringa. Jacobi considers it incredible that Paul arbitrarily inserted Scoringa and Mauringa, and he believes that these names were in the original copy of the Origo which Paul used.</p>
        <p>According to Jacobi (p. 16), Vesme’s view that everything Paul did not borrow from the Origo and Gregory of Tours regarding the early history of his people comes from the lost work of Secundus, has been refuted by Waitz (Götting gel. Anz. 1856, p. 1587). Everything which can be traced with certainty to Secundus indicates that the lost work of that author had an annalistic form.</p>
        <p>The statements of the wandering from Mauringa to Vurgundaib, Paul takes almost word for word (I, 13) from the Origo. His account of the elevation of king Agelmund to the throne (I, 14) and the thirty-three-year reign of that monarch does not vary from his copy, but the motive for the selection of a king appears to be Paul’s own addition. It is the same which was attributed to the Israelites when Saul was made their king (I Samuel VIII, 5) “Now make us a king to judge us like all the nations” (Jacobi, 17).</p>
        <p>Paul then mentions Lamissio as the second king (P. I, 17) but relates much more than stands in the Origo which simply declares, “After Agilmund, reigned Laimicho of the race of Gugingus.” It appears to Jacobi that all this addition comes from another source, since departing from the Origo, Lamissio’s monstrous birth and rescue from the pond by king Agelmund is stated (I, 15) while his six brothers are drowned, and afterwards the Langobards pass over a river and fight with the Amazons. Neither can the defeat of the Langobards by the Bulgarians nor the liberation of the people through Lamissio’s boldness be traced to the Origo, but Paul returns to that account when he mentions the succession of king Lethu and the two following kings (chap. 18), and the taking possession of Rugiland by the Langobards (Paul, ch. 19; Jacobi, p. 19). This short account of the Origo, Paul amplifies with additions from Eugippius’s Life of St. Severinus and from the Chronicle of Jordanis. According to the Origo he then mentions the death of Godeoc, the succession of Claffo and Tato, the emigration of the Langobards from Rugiland, their three years’ stay in the open “feld,” the war of Tato with Rodolf, king of the Heroli, the overthrow of the latter and the capture of his banner and his helmet (ch. 20). On the other hand Paul gives as the cause of the war the murder of Rodolf’s brother at the instigation of Rumetruda and describes the fight in detail from an unknown source and he then comes back to the Origo with the statement that Tato carried off the standard of Rodolf. Here two sources can clearly be distinguished (Jacobi, 20).  Tato’s overthrow by Waccho (whom Paul erroneously makes the son of Zuchilo); Waccho’s contest with Hildechis; the flight of the latter to the Gepidae; the enmity thereafter between the two peoples and the subjugation of the Suevi by Waccho are reported by Paul from the Origo without variation. From the same source he enumerates the three wives of Waccho and their children, but with Ranicunda he leaves out the name of her father. He calls Austrigusa a daughter of the king of the Gepidae (I, 21), departing from the Origo which called her a girl of the Gepidae. Waltari, Waccho’s son is called in the Origo <I>farigaidus</I>, “without descendants,” an adjective lacking in Paul (Jacobi, 21). Audoin’s expedition to Pannonia (I, 22) and the name of his wife Rodelinda (I, 27) are taken from the Origo.<ref type="note" target="28" /> On the other hand Paul introduces from another source the account (I, 23-24) of the duel of Alboin with Turismod the son of Turisind and the expedition to the latter king to get his arms. Paul takes from the Origo the account of Alboin’s first marriage with Chlotsuinda; the battle with the Gepidae and the marriage of Alboin with Rosemund (I, 27), but he makes two additions; one that Alboin found support from the Avars and the other that the skull of Cunimund was used as a drinking-cup. Since Paul says (II, 28) he saw this drinking vessel in the hand of king Ratchis, perhaps that king is our author’s authority. Menander (Exc. legatt, p. 303, 304, Bonn. ed.) confirms the statement that the Langobards had the help of the Avars (Jacobi, 22). Paul now follows other sources and returns to the Origo when he states that Alboin by treaty relinquished Pannonia to the Avars (II, 7). The three manuscripts of La Cava, Madrid and Modena here give evidence of an important omission. The Chronicon Gothanum alone has kept the account of this matter<ref type="note" target="29" /> and Jacobi considers that from this place on it gives us the better text. The story that Narses called the Langobards into the country occurs in the Origo, but Paul here gives the preference to another and more complete source, the Liber Pontificalis. On the other hand he gives from the Origo (and incorrectly) the stay of the Langobards in Pannonia as forty-two years, also the date of their emigration as the second of April; the fact that Easter fell upon the first of April in the year 568 is correctly reckoned up by Paul himself (II, 7). The mention of the year of our Lord probably comes from another source, perhaps Secundus.</p>
        <p>The account of Alboin’s murder in Verona (II, 28) is traceable in some features to the Origo, but Paul relates in detail the adultery of Rosemund on which the Origo is silent but which the Langobard chronicle for the year 641 confirms. Whence Paul got his account can scarcely be determined (Jacobi, 22). The statement of Helmechis’ vain attempt to obtain the crown, his flight with Rosemund, Albsuinda and the royal treasure to Ravenna, and the fate which there overtook the conspirators (II, 29) were taken by Paul from the Origo, also the statement that Albsuinda was sent tt Constantinople with the treasure (II, 30). We next meet with the Origo in the execution of the rebellious duks Mimulf (IV, 3), Zangrulf and Gaidulf (IV, 13), but the repeated rebellions of the latter, Paul took from another source. He appears to have inserted from the Origo the statement that Gunduald was duke of Asti (IV, 40), as well as the account of the conquests of Rothari (IV, 45) and his victory at the Scultenna.</p>
        <p>The forgoing is Jacobi’s opinion as to the use of the Origo.</p>
        <p>According to Mommsen’s view (Neues Arciv, V, 58) Paul had before him a source that was far more copious, and from the condensed Origo as we have it and Paul’s narrative taken together, there can be formed a combination nearer the original than either.<ref type="note" target="30" /> Even in Paul’s time there were manuscripts of the laws of the Langobards which did not contain the Origo, and of the numerous ones which have come down to us only three, all of the 10th and 11th century, have the Origo, and that in different forms, besides the Chronicon Gothanum from a single manuscript of the 11th century, with still greater variations; Mommsen therefore considers it probable that at a later time this historical introduction to Rothari’s laws, where not omitted, was adopted only in abbreviated form (p. 59). He adds that the Chronicon Gothanum contain certain statements not found in the other three manuscripts, but which certainly belong to the original, and some of which are also found in Paul. Among these is the statement that when the Langobards, before their emigration from Pannonia, turned over all their territory to the Avars, the latter agreed to evacuate it if the Langobards should be driven from Italy (I, 27; II, 7), and that no other explanation is possible, except that the Origo omitted this account. Mommsen here compares the opening statements of the Origo with Paul (I, 2 and 3) and adds (p. 63) that the account of the over-population of Scadinavia, the division of its inhabitants into three parts and the emigration of one-third is found only with Paul, although its saga-like form indicates that it is borrowed from the Origo in which the abbreviated words “among these (<I>inter quos</I>) was a small people that was called the Winnilis” represent this account. The remark of Paul, that besides over-population other causes of their emigration are also asserted, points to the fact that the complete Origo added something further, perhaps of floods or failure of crops or similar afflictions.<ref type="note" target="31" /></p>
        <p>Mommsen (p. 64) here compares the accounts in the Origo and in Paul regarding the origin of the name of the Langobards and the victory given to the Winnili by Wotan. He notes (p. 65) that Scoringa is mentioned only by Paul, and that in the Origo no place is assigned to the battle, and he adds: “That this is the result of an abbreviation appears clearly from the expression which follows, ‘And the Langobards moved <I>thence</I> and came into Golaida,’ while no place is mentioned previously except Scadanan, and the word ‘thence’ is therefore without relation to anything which precedes.” The account of the famine (p. 66) is found only in Paul; also the opposition of the Assipitti, the story of the men with the dogs’ heads, of the duel of the Langobard slave with the champion of the Assipitti, of emancipation by the arrow, and finally of the immigration into Mauringa. For none of these legends is there any statement which explains their origin, and Mommsen insists that they fit excellently into the Origo. He adds: “With the emigration into Golaida both the accounts again come together. The Origo says: ‘And the Langobards moved <I>thence</I> and came into Golaida, and afterwards they possessed the aldionates of Anthaib and Bainaib, and also Burgundaib.’ Paul says (I, 13): ‘Then the Langobards went forth from Mauringa and arrived in Golanda, where, having remained some time, they are afterwards said to have possessed for some years Anthab, Banthab, and also Vurgundaib, which we can consider are names of districts (cantons) or of some kinds of places.’ Here it appears clearly that the Origo is abbreviated; that the four oldest abodes of the Langobards, Scadinavia, Scoringa, Mauringa and Golanda, belong to a connected legend will hardly be contested, but as the Origo now stands, the Winniles come from Scadanan to Golaida, and of their four abodes the second and third are lacking, although in the word ‘thence’ the trace of an intermediate station is seen” (p. 67). </p>
        <p>“The account (p. 68) of the ignoble birth of the second king Lamissio  *  *  * is lacking in the Origo, but Bethmann says, incorrectly (Waitz, note 1, 15), that it contradicts the Origo. The words ‘of the race of Gugingus’ which are added both in the Origo and Paul to the name of the first king (Agelmund) are added to that of the second (Lamissio) only in one edition of the Origo.<ref type="note" target="32" /> and are a palpable interpolation, since the name of the family is not given in the case of any later king, and in the list of kings incorporated in Rothari’s laws the family name is affixed only in the case of the first king.”</p>
        <p>Mommsen (p. 71) observes that in the account of Rosemund and Alboin the condensation in the Origo is again evident, that it is improbable that a story-teller who reports with such particularity how Frea turned around her husband’s bed should have left out of the Rosemund story the goblet made of the king’s skull, but that with epitomizers everything is possible, and not the least to leave out the point of the story.  “It is not clear,” he adds, “how the rôles in this tragedy were distributed. According to the Origo, Alboin was killed by Rosemund and Helmechis by the counsel of Peredeo. According to Paul, Helmechis, the armor-bearer of the king, procures Peredeo as an unwilling confederate, and it is then said, ‘According to the counsel of Peredeo, she, more cruel than any beast, introduced the murderer Helmechis.’ ”</p>
        <p>“It looks as if Paul had not properly understood his copy, for which the latter was in fault, and therefore wrote something that makes no clear sense.”<ref type="note" target="33" /></p>
        <p>Mommsen thus continues (p. 72).  “Waitz adopts for the Langobardic sections of Paul’s history a triple source; first, the Origo; second, another narrative which related divers matters concerning the abodes and migration of that people, (the contradictions between which two sources Paul either does not notice or has not considered worthy of regard), and finally the writing of Secundus concerning the acts of the Langobards. That the first two sources are rather to be combined into one has been shown in the previous argument. Of contradictions I see simply nothing, since the discrepancies in regard to the origin of Lamissio and the murder of Alboin depend respectively upon a mistake of the text and an erroneous interpretation; but the harmonizing of both versions appears to me easy and natural.”</p>
        <p>“It is quite different with the writing of Secundus of Trent. Paul mentions this work twice (III, 29; IV, 40) under the title ‘The Acts of the Langobards.’ A series of statements can be traced with complete certainty to this authority, partly on account of personal references and partly on account of the places where they occurred. This has ofen been done, and was done in a satisfactory way by Jacobi (p. 65 <I>et seq.</I>).  *  *  * If it is to be accepted with good reason that the historical accounts in Paul for the time before 612, so far as they depend upon a Langobard source, ought to be traced to Secundus, it appears all the more difficult to determine the relation of Secundus to the Origo. It is pure caprice to attribute with Jacobi the accounts which bear a legendary character to the Origo and contemporaneous statements to Secundus. It is a peculiarity of the earlier Langobard history to mingle truth and poetry indistinguishably even in matters which are not properly legendary, in the case of Rosemund’s crime and Authari’s wooing. On the one hand the Origo included the later times of Langobard history, and on the other, the title of Secundus’ book is opposed to the idea that he wrote only the history of his own time (p. 73).  *  *  *  Besides, in the occurrences under Agilulf (A. D. 590 to 616) which properly fall in the time of Secundus, the close relationship between the Origo and Paul is still preserved. Moreover, the early Langobard tradition in Paul has a homogeneous character and there is scarcely room in it for more than one authority.”</p>
        <p>“There is only one way out of this embarrassment, but nothing hinders us from taking it. Is it not evident that the Origo Gentis Langobardorum is nothing but an extract from the writing of Secundus of Trent furnished with a short continuation? Then everything explains itself simply. The Origo was prefixed as an historical introduction to the laws of the Langobards, possibly upon their issue in 643, or probably in 668. How should the man who did this have been ignorant of the chronicle of Secundus of Trent which had been brought down to 612? Nothing is more probable than that Secundus was used for this purpose and that the editor limited himself to continuing it up to the time he wrote. That Paul cited the book as the Prologue of the Edict of king Rothari, according to its official position, when he wanted to defend himself against the reproach of the falsification of history and that he elsewhere called it the “Acts of the Langobards” of Secundus is not opposed to this (?). Once admit that the historical work was a component part of the book of laws as Paul at least considered it, and nothing can be objected to both these designations (p. 74).”</p>
        <p>Schmidt (Neues Archiv, 13, p. 391) supports Mommsen’s contention that the copy of the Origo from which Paul took his extracts was more extensive than the manuscripts which have come down to us. He remarks that as Paul did not find the account of the subjugation of the Suevi by king Waccho in <I>all</I> his copies, abbreviated editions must have been before him, and the statements in Paul’s history which are not in our present texts of the Origo must be traced to some earlier and fuller edition of that work<ref type="note" target="34" />  (p. 392 <I>et seq.</I>).</p>
        <p>But Schmidt considers Mommsen’s view, that this original Origo was identical with Secundus, as not tenable and believes with Jacobi that the latter work was more in the nature of annals (p. 394). Ebert also (Litteratur des Mittelalters, II, 46, note 1) insists that the book from which Mommsen declares Paul had taken so much, could not be the “succinct little history” which Paul described in book IV, chapter 40.</p>
        <p>Waitz (Neues Archiv, Vol. V, p. 421) thus answers Mommsen’s contention: “For myself I can in no way consider probable the view that the so-called Origo, the Chronicon Gothanum and Paul have drawn from a common source, and that their contents are to be traced back in great part to the lost book of Secundus. I will never convince myself that Paul has cited the same work at one time, as ‘The Acts of the Langobards,’ of this author and at another time as a prologue to an edict.  *  *  * I also see no ground whatever to consider the Origo an extract from a greater work, an extract which according to Mommsen’s view must have simply omitted important occasions in the History of the Langobards. In the words which are introduced as a proof or mark of the abbreviation, ‘And the Langobards moved thence,’ the word ‘thence’ related to Scadinavia or Scadanan. The Origo gives us the tradition in regard to the naming of the Langobards in naïve originality. It lets the people receive their name in the place where their first home was, and it inquires little whether there were Wandals there or not. I can only consider it one of the arbitrary combinations of Paul when he puts the story during the emigration to the land of Soringa.  *  *  *</p>
        <p>“Mommsen seeks to remove a contradiction between the statement of the Origo regarding the ancestry of Laiamicho and the detailed narrative given by Paul of the birth of Lamissio, as the king is here called, by removing the words ‘from the race of Gugingus’ with one manuscript out of the text. But this manuscript (p. 423), or as Mommsen writes it, this recension is troubled with mistakes of all kinds, and it must appear unjustified to give it the preference in one place where it seems to fit. The same words are also left out in the manuscript immediately before, with reference to Agelmund, and only later are restored to the margin, which can easily have been forgotten the second time. We cannot therefore speak here of an erroneous text.”</p>
        <p>As to Paul’s mistaken interpretation of the account of Alboin’s murder, which Mommsen thinks is due to the fault in the source from which he took the account, Waitz remarks: “It constantly appears to me, on the other hand, that he has transcribed his copy, especially in the Origo, only too faithfully,<ref type="note" target="35" /> without remarking that the detailed narrative which he previously followed, divides the rôles otherwise —; assigns the advice to Helmechis and the act to Peredeo.”</p>
        <p>An interesting light is now thrown upon this discussion by the skillful efforts of Bruckner and others to trace the Origo to a Langobard epic song. Bruckner Sprache der Langobarden, (p. 17 <I>et seq.</I>) observes that although no remnant of Langobard poetry has come down to us in ts original form, yet there is evidence that such poetry existed, and certain features in the Origo as preserved in the Latin language indicate that its statements were taken at least in part from a Langobard poem. In the first place, the word <I>farigaidus,</I><ref type="note" target="36" /> “without posterity,” is a sure proof that the author made use of a German source. In the next place, the alliteration in the first chapters which was noticed by Müllenhof (Beowulf, 101), Schmidt (p. 16) and Koegel (I, 107) is made apparent by the re-translation into Old-German of portions of the first four chapters. Bruckner accordingly gives a number of such translations, showing alliteration. His view was contested by Much (Götting gel. Anzeiger, 1896, p. 892) and also by Kraus (Zeitschrift für osterreichischen Gymnasien, 1895, Vol. 47, pp. 313, 314) who showed the objections to such re-translations and claimed that alliterative proper names did not prove that a song was the immediate source from which the Latin account was taken. By way of illustration Kraus translated into German a passage taken haphazard from Livy, and the translation certainly showed a goodly number of alliterative words. Kraus therefore insisted that the traces of alliteration must be much more numerous and evident than those given by Bruckner to exclude the suspicion of accident. Bruckner then, in an article in the ”Zeitschrift für deutsches Alterthum” (Vol. 43, part I, (p. 47), answers these criticisms.</p>
        <p>He treats the Origo, not as a whole, but in single parts separated from each other (p. 48). The first chapter tells how the Wandals and Winnili encounter each other ready for battle; how Frea interferes in a cunning manner in favor of the Winnili, and how Wotan then gave to them the name of Langobards, and the victory over their enemies.  “It is hard to see,” says Bruckner, “how the legend of the origin of this people, in which myth and history appear closely united, could have been transmitted to subsequent generations otherwise than in epic song. Original nationality expresses itself in the whole delightful and simple narrative. Learned accessories are wholly absent. We have in this first chapter an old saga of the people in unadulterated form.  *  *  * The conduct of Frea toward Godan reminds one of that of Hera toward Zeus as described in the Iliad<ref type="note" target="37" /> (Book 14, line 153). In the songs of the Edda similar contrivances are related of the gods.  *  *  *</p>
        <p>“The account of the Origo shows the essential characteristics of an epic song. The action is related in a concise but powerful manner, mostly in the shape of a dialogue, and althoughthe account is relatively a short one, the repetitions characteristic of epic poetry are not lacking. For example, ‘Then the leaders of the Wandals, Ambri and Assi moved’ and shortly afterwards ‘Then Ambri and Assi, that is the leaders of the Wandals.’ Again ‘They besought Frea, the wife of Godan’ and a few lines later ‘Frea the wife of Godan turned the bed around.’ It corresponds moreover with the epic style that the counsel which Frea gives the Winniles and its results are related with the same expressions almost word for word.  ‘Then Frea gave the advice that when the sun rose the Winniles should come, and that their women, with their hair let down around the face, etc,’ and again, ‘And he (Godan), looking upon them, saw the Winniles and their women with their hair let down around the face.’ According to the custom of epic poetry of seizing only the principal events of the action, the carrying out of this counsel on the part of the Winniles is not related of itself, but after the advice is given them it is straightway shown how Godan sees them, together with their women, on awakening.”  *  *  *</p>
        <p>“In the Origo, on account of the simple mode of presentation, the traces of alliteration are so clear and extensive as to exclude the possibility that they are due to accident. One peculiarity, which shows an original composition in verse, is that the action moves in strikingly short sentences or in sharply marked divisions of sentences which correspond in length to a half verse. This circumstance is all the more important when the different character of the construction of sentences in Latin is considered, and this division of verse results naturally and without any effort to produce it.”</p>
        <p>Bruckner now attempts the task of reconstructing the Origo in the form of a German song. He makes no effort to use any conjectural inflected form, but puts the substantive in the nominative and the verb in the infinitive, and thus reconstructs metrically the greater part of the first chapter. There are a few passages that cannot be reproduced in alliterative verse if no change is made, and some of his proposed translations may be questioned, but he insists that there is enough remaining to show the epic origin of the Origo. The following extract, beginning at the second sentence of the Origo (where the poem probably commenced) shows this effort of reproduction:</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="50" />“There was a small people that was called Winnilis,</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="51" />And with them was a woman, Gambara by name, and she had</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="52" />two sons. </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="53" />Ibor was the name of one and Agio the name of the other. </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="54" />They with their mother, Gambara by name,</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="55" />Held the sovereignty over the Winniles. Moved then</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="56" />The leaders of the Wandals, that is, Ambri and Assi, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="57" />With their army and said to the Winniles, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="58" />Either pay tributes or prepare yourselves</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="59" />For battle and fight with us. </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="60" />Then answered Ibor and Agio</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="61" />With their mother Gambara, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="62" />It is better for us to make ready the battle</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="63" />Than to pay tributes to the Wandals.</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="64" />Then Ambri and Assi, that is, the leaders of the Wandals, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="65" />Asked Wodan that over the Winniles</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="66" />He should give them the victory.</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="67" />Wodan answered and said,</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="68" />Whom at sunrise I shall first see, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="69" />To them will I give the victory.</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="70" />At that time Gambara with her two sons, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="71" />That is, Ibor and Agio, who were chiefs over the Winniles, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="72" />Besought Frea, the wife of Wodan, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="73" />To be propitious to the Winniles.</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="74" />Then Frea gave counsel that at sunrise </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="75" />The Winniles should come, and that their women,</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="76" />With their hair let down around their face </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="77" />In the likeness of a beard, should come also with their husbands.</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="78" />Then when it became bright, while the sun was rising, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="79" />Frea, the wife of Wodan, turned around</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="80" />The bed where her husband was lying</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="81" />And put his face toward the east</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="82" />And awakened him, and he, looking at them, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="83" />Saw the Winniles and their women</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="84" />Having their hair let down around the face,</p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="85" />And he says, ‘Who are these long-beards?’ </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="86" />And Frea said to Wodan, </p>
        <p><ref type="note" target="87" />As thou hast given a name, give them also the victory.”<ref type="note" target="39" /></p>
        <p>In the concluding passage —; “And he gave them the victory so that they should defend themselves according to his counsel and obtain the victory. From that time the Winnili were called Langobards” —; there are also traces of alliteration, but there is evidently a defect in the translation or a change from the original form, and there is some contradiction between the manuscripts.</p>
        <p>The next chapter, which tells of the emigration of the Langobards, the election of their king, and the succession of the two subsequent kings, also contains national traditions, and in like manner the elements of alliterative verse appear in it, as well in the third chapter, describing the fight between king Odoacar and the Rugians and the settlement of the Langobards in Rugiland. The same is true of the earlier parts of Chapter IV. In this chapter the battle between Tato and Rodolf, king of the Heroli, is described. In Paul’s History of the Langobards (I, 20) ware told: “Tato indeed carried off the banner of Rodolf, which they call <I>bandum</I>, and his helmet which he had been accustomed to bear in war.” Bruckner believes (p. 55) that the redundant clause, “Which he had been accustomed to bear in war,” can only be explained as a translation of a German composite word; that the combat between the Langobards and the Heroli was celebrated in a German song, and that the traces of this song appear in what precedes and follows.<ref type="note" target="40" /></p>
        <p>In the latter part of the fourth chapter, however (Bruckner, p. 57), the tractes of alliteration begin to disappear at the passage, ‘And Wacho fought and Ildichis, the son of Tato, fought and Ildichis fled to the Gippidi where he died, etc.’ The rest of chapter IV shows few recognizable traces of alliterative song. The account of the three wives of Wacho and his various children evidently comes from another source. Only three lines (describing Wacho’s death, that his son Waltari reigned seven years, and that these were Lethinges) are alliterative. After these Bruckner finds no traces of a poeti source and considers that this part of the Origo is rather historical than traditional, that it shows a style quite different from the first part, with more involved construction and indirect quotations, and the impossibility of turning it into alliterative verse seems to him to show all the more clearly that the first part of the poem, which can be so easily done into such verse, has a poetical origin.</p>
        <p>It appears to the present translator that Bruckner has made out his case, and that in his reconstruction of these alliterative verses he has shown the strongest probability of the epic origin of the first part of the Origo.</p>
        <p>In regard to the general question as to the source from which Paul derived his account, Bruckner in this article (p. 47) follows the opinion of Waitz, and whereas Mommsen sees no contradiction between Paul and the Origo, Bruckner considers that Paul’s account varies so widely from it that even a common source cannot be inferred!</p>
        <p>In the presence of such divergent views, it is hazardous for the editor to venture an opinion. It seems to him, however, that Waitz and Bruckner have effectually refuted Mommsen’s contention that Paul drew his account from a single and more extensive Origo contained in the lost historical work of Secundus. Paul’s own statement (I, 21) shows that he consulted, not only one, but several manuscripts in regard to the early history of his people. He would hardly have given two different titles to the single work of Secundus. The fact that the Origo came originally from an epic poem makes it improbable that an historical work should have been the single source from which it was derived. It is more than likely that one or more of the manuscripts Paul consulted were similar in scope and phraseology to the Origo as we have it, and that he made extracts therefrom almost word for word.<ref type="note" target="41" /></p>
        <p>Waitz’s contention that there were three sources: first, the Origo as we have it, second, some other account not known to us, and third, Secundus of Trent, seems highly probable. This second source, however, may well have been a more extended version of the Origo than that preserved in the three manuscripts of Madrid, La Cava and Modena. The evidence of abbreviation in these manuscripts as set forth by Mommsen and Schmidt as well as Jacobi,<ref type="note" target="42" /> is quite strong.</p>
        <p>The fact that the Origo was taken in part from an epic poem does not conflict with this view. Upon the whole, Waitz’s opinion appears to the editor to be sound, with the understanding that the “other source” he speaks of may well have been another version of the Origo in a greatly extended and somewhat altered form.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="notes">
        <note id="6"> Bethmann refers <I>quem</I> to <I>edicti</I> following a grammatical mistake in the edict itself. Vesme refers it to <I>prologum</I> implying that Paul considered Rothari the author of the prologue (see Jacobi, 5).</note>
        <note id="7"> These manuscripts are described in Bethmann, 356 to 360. There is much difference of opinion as to which is the best. Bruckner (Zeitschrift für deutsches Alterthum, vol. 34, pt. 1, p. 49, note) considers the Modena more ancient and original than the Madrid. Also Schmidt (p. 9) who among many reasons refers to the correct spelling of Winniles, Waltari, Walderada instead of Guinniles, Gualtari, Gualderada. Mommsen speaks of the Madrid and La Cava MSS. as the two best (p. 37, note) but says the choice of the reading is free and that sometimes the Modena is more correct (id., 60, note 2). The Madrid MSS. closed A. D. 671, the Modena A. D. 668, and Waitz has shown that in so far the latter stood nearer the original form (id.). </note>
        <note id="8"> I follow the edition of Waitz in Monumenta Germaniae Historica —; Scriptores Rerum Langobardicarum, pp. 1-6.</note>
        <note id="9"> The Madrid and La Cava manuscripts in place of “There is an island” have “That is under the consul” which is evidently a corruption (see Mommsen, p. 60, note 2).</note>
        <note id="10">  “Scadan” says the Modena MS., “Scandanan,” the La Cava MS.</note>
        <note id="11">  <I>Exscidia</I> (Modena MSS.). A derivation pointing to the Gothic word <I>skattigan</I>, to injure, German <I>Schaden</I>, English <I>scathe</I> (Hodg., VI, 90). Mommsen considers this a later interpolation to be rejected (p. 60, note 3).  </note>
        <note id="12"> The words “Of the face of Gugingus” are omitted in the Modena MSS. and Mommsen regards them (p. 68) as an interpolation (see also Brückner, Zeitschrift für deutsche Alterthum, p. 56)</note>
        <note id="13"> Jacobi, 20, note 4.</note>
        <note id="14"> Read <I>regi</I> with Modena MS. in place of <I>regis</I>.</note>
        <note id="15">  “<I>Farigaidus</I>” (Bruckner, pp. 19, 203).</note>
        <note id="16">  “Of the stock of Gausus” says the list of kings in Rothari’s Prologue (Mon. Germ. Hist. Leges, IV, 2).</note>
        <note id="17"> The Modena MS. says twelve. Neither number is correct. They probably remained there about twenty-two years.</note>
        <note id="18">  <I>A Pascha</I>, (Waitz, p. 11, 7, note).</note>
        <note id="19"> Thus Abel translates <I>in caldo</I> (p. 6), or perhaps it is “In a hot potion.”</note>
        <note id="20"> Aggo in Modena MSS.</note>
        <note id="21">  <I>Turingus</I>. Perhaps this merely means that he was duke of Turin.  “Of the stock of Anawas” adds the Prologue to Rothari’s Edict (Mon. Germ. Hist. Leges, Vol. IV, p. 2).   </note>
        <note id="22">  “And a son named Adwald” adds the Modena MSS.</note>
        <note id="23"> In the Prologue, “Arioald of the race of Caupus.” The text here seems greatly corrupted. Paul and the Chronicon Gothanum give Agilulf’s reign at 25 years and that of his son Adalwald (here omitted) at 10 years.</note>
        <note id="24"> Northwest of Lucca.</note>
        <note id="25"> In Modena.</note>
        <note id="26"> The Modena MSS. adds “seventeen years.”</note>
        <note id="27"> The Modena MSS. omits the sentence regarding Berthari.</note>
        <note id="28"> The Chronicon Gothanum calls Audoin’s mother “Menia the wife of king Pissa,” and speaks of him as of the race of Gausus (M. G. LL., IV, 644). Paul and the Origo make no mention of the matter.</note>
        <note id="29"> It states: “At this time when the Langobards began to go out of Pannonia, the Avars then made an agreement and treaty of friendship with those Langobards and a document of writing, that up to two hundred years if they should again seek Pannonia, they (the Avars) would relinquish to their side that land without any wars of contest and would be ready for their assistance in Italy to which they had set out, up to full two hundred years” (M. G. LL., IV, p. 644).</note>
        <note id="30"> Bethmann also says the Chronicon Gothanum sometimes contains matters lacking in the Origo but which are found in Paul who did not use the Chronicon Gothanum, and that these things must have existed in the common source of both the Origo and Chronicon Gothanum (p. 364).</note>
        <note id="31"> May not the reason given in the Chronicon Gothanum (M. G. LL., IV, 641), that “the people were moved, not by necessity or hardness of heart, or oppression of the poor, but that they should attain salvation from on high,” be one of the causes to which Paul refers (Schmidt, Neues Archiv, XIII, 392, note 1)?</note>
        <note id="32"> That of the La Cava and Madrid MSS. which are closely allied. They are omitted in the Modena MS.</note>
        <note id="33"> Does it not rather look as if he took his account from two contradictory sources which he tried to reconcile in his usual inconclusive way just as he made Odoacar king of part of the Rugians (I, 19) at a time when he was fighting against the Rugians?</note>
        <note id="34"> The totally varying statements of the time of Agilulf’s reign, six years according to the Origo and twenty-five, according to Paul are due to the great corruption of the manuscripts in this place (compare the various readings in Waitz’s ed.).</note>
        <note id="35"> Paul (II, 28), “Rosemund  *  *  *  * according to the advice of Peredeo brought in the murderer Helmichis.” Origo, “He was killed in Verona in the palace by Hilmichis and Rosemund his wife upon the advice of Peritheo.”</note>
        <note id="36"> Or <I>fargaetum</I> as the Chronicon Gothanum has it. Bethmann considers this word related to the modern German <I>vergessen</I>, “forgotten” (M. G., Script. Rerum Langob., p. 4), and thinks it is a mere author’s note of something forgotten.</note>
        <note id="37"> After the Trojans under the guidance of Zeus had attacked the Greeks by their swift ships, and were defeating them, Hera borrowed the girdle of Aphrodite, secured the aid of Sleep, and beguiled Zeus into a deep slumber, whereupon the Greeks, aided by Poseidon, defeated the Trojans and drove them back.</note>
        <note id="38"> The Godan of the Latin text is probably a corruption of Wotan or Wodan (see Paul, I, 9).</note>
        <note id="39"> It will be noted that four out of the six lines in the foregoing, which it is impossible to render into alliterative German, are those relating to Gambara, so that a single interpolation or defect in the translation into Latin might account for them all. Every one of these four lines might be omitted, and scarcely any change would be required in the rest of the the poem. May it not be that the statements concerning Gambara came from another source?</note>
        <note id="40"> If this is so it would seem to indicate —; since the phrase “which he had been accustomed to bear in war” does not appear in the Origo —; that Paul had taken his account from some different (perhaps more extended) version which had also for its source an epic poem.</note>
        <note id="41"> Bluhme in his preface to the Laws of the Langobards (Mon. Germ. Hist. LL., IV, cxii, sec. x) states that the Madrid and La Cava MSS. came from Benevento. If so, their prototypes were probably accessible to Paul.</note>
        <note id="42"> See also Bethmann, 364.</note>
        <!--start of creative writing notes and note: not all poetry lines have notes-->
        <note id="50">                                  werod                             Winnilis</note>
        <note id="53"> Ibor                                             Agio</note>
        <note id="55">                 gi<I>w</I>ald                          <I>W</I>inneles   ar<I>w</I>egan</note>
        <note id="56">         erl (or adaling                               Ambri        Assi</note>
        <note id="57">                    werod                           Winniles</note>
        <note id="58">             gamban geldan garuuian</note>
        <note id="59">        wîg            winnan.</note>        
        <note id="60">      anduuordian Ibor        Agio</note>
        <note id="62">         bazzira                                           badu</note>
        <note id="63">                gamban geldan       gairewandilum</note>
        <note id="64">           Ambri         Assi                      erl (adaling)</note>
        <note id="65">             Wôdan<ref type="note" target="38" />                       Winniles</note>
        <note id="66">                    saljan              sigu</note>
        <note id="67"> Wôdan                          wordun sprak</note>
        <note id="68">                  sunna upstîgan air sehan</note>
        <note id="69">                           salgan   sigu</note>
        <note id="71">               Ibor        Agio                    adaling or erl</note>
        <note id="72">                  Frea         fri</note>
        <note id="73">            wegôn? (Old-High-German) Winniles</note>
        <note id="74">                                 râd                 u<I>rr</I>isan</note>
        <note id="75">         Winniles                                                  wîb</note>
        <note id="76">                     hâr                                          hleor</note>
        <note id="77"> gi<I>l</I>inissie                                                                       liudweros (?)]</note>
        <note id="78">                                        suigli (?)               sunna</note>
        <note id="79"> Frea        fri</note>
        <note id="81">                        andwlita            austar</note>
        <note id="82">         wakjan                             wlîtan</note>
        <note id="83">                Winniles                  wîb</note>
        <note id="84">                         hâr                                      hleor</note>
        <note id="86">                  wordun sprak Wôdan</note>
        <note id="87">                                                  saljan                      sigu</note>
    </div>
    </text>
</TEI>
